<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Awakened Flame</name>
		<description> Homebrew Race created and uploaded to the D&D Wiki.</description>
		<author url="https://www.dandwiki.com/wiki/Awakened_Flame_(5e_Race)"></author>
		<update version="0.0.1">
			<file name="race-awakened_flame.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Sworn115/Homebrew-Files-for-Aurora/main/race-awakened_flame.xml">
		</update>
	</info>
	
	<element name="Awakened Flame" type="Race" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACE_AWAKENED_FLAME">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">A pot of awakening, a potion of awaken, an awakened heart, whatever it was that awoke the mind of an awakened creature, it 
			brought life and intelligence to be within the creature, and in the case of the awakened flame, it could be 
			anything. But most importantly, the heart of an awakened flame is made of pure fire, in fact the entirety of 
			an awakened flame is fire, they aren't quite elementals but share many of the same aspects and behaviours 
			as them, except an awakened fire has much more control over their form, as rather than being a creature of 
			fire magic, they are pure sentient fire.</p>
			<h4>Physical Description</h4>
			<p>An awakened flame is an ordinary fire source given sentience and mobility by the Awaken spell or similar 
			magic. Awakened flame do not have a gender but are able to change their form and shape to match such if they 
			wish to simulate one or a specific appearance is desired.</p>
			<p class="indent">Awakened flame have a thin layer of solidified substance, presumed to be made of a form of 
			thick mist, this mist is what holds them together and allows them to take physical forms, when injured the 
			mist breaks, allowing their internal flames to escape, when this happens the mist will rush to accommodate, 
			in an effort to patch the hole as quick as possible. This usually results in loss of size and weight, and 
			as the awakened flame's health gets lower, so does it's size.</p>
			<h4>History</h4>
			<p>The Awakened flame's history is similar to any other awakened's history, they came to being. Many stories 
			are told about the history of Awakened, but their entire history can usually boil down to one aspect, they 
			are simply creations of ordinary objects being given the gift of sentience, intelligence and mobility.</p>
			<p class="indent">They tend to roam in hot or warm environments, as it's the safest place for them, they may 
			stay living on their own within a volcanic or assist other races by acting as a fire of some sort, aiding 
			lost adventurers in the cold nights, or working with blacksmiths in whom they've become great friends with, 
			but some may leave their home to explore or join societies of other awakened, such as other awakened 
			creatures. Some awakened flame even find their way into the fire plane, where they are the absolute safest, 
			as the safest place to be as a being of pure fire is within the realm of flames.</p>
			<p class="indent">An awakened flame may be made of pure fire but don't let their appearance fool you, while 
			their form is impermanent, they are still capable of taking a hit or two, and are even more capable of 
			dishing it back out. An awakened flame can learn many different offensive techniques, their most prominent 
			ones being their ability to easily evade attacks and turn their own bodies into natural weapons. As being 
			made of entirely fire, bruises and slashes don't stay for long. If they even stay.</p>
			<h4>Awakened Flame Names</h4>
			<p>Awakened flame tend to give themselves names, they are beings of pure fire and as such do not know 
			much about naming themselves, they've often taken on names of their own environment.</p>
			<p>
			<span class="feature">Omnisex Names:</span>Igni, Scorch, Burns, Magma, Torch, Heat, Blaze, Inferna, 
			Char, Ember, Flare, Tinder, Pyro, Calcifer<br />
			</p>
			<h4>Awakened Flame Traits</h4>
			<p>Awakened Sentient Beings of Pure Fire.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> Your Constitution score increases
			by 2.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Age.</em></strong> Awakened flame are pure fire, and as such their life span 
			is infinite for as long as they hold onto the magic that keeps them awakened.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Alignment.</em></strong> Awakened flame are wild beings, they are either chaotic
			or neutral and are usually good.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> Awakened flame vary extremely in height and build, from barely 
			5 feet to well over 6 feet tall. Your size is Medium.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your base walking speed is 25 feet. Your base flying speed is 
			30 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Lit Flame.</em></strong> You gain darkvision with a 60-foot range. 
			Additionally you shed bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Scorch Skin.</em></strong> When a creature within 5 feet of you deals 
			damage to you or touches your surface flame with any part of their own body. The creature takes 1 fire
			damage. You can not wear flammable armor, such as leather or hide.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Snuffed Flame.</em></strong> When subjected to an effect or spell that 
			would normally snuff or put out open flames, you are immune to any portion of the spell that would 
			extinguish you, however your speed is reduced by 20-feet until the end of your next turn.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Pure Fire.</em></strong> You have immunity to fire damage. However if you 
			make any significant contact with water you take cold damage equal to your level, doubled if more than 
			1/2 your body is submerged. You know the cantrip control flame, Constitution is your spellcasting ability 
			for this cantrip.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Made of Fire.</em></strong> Your body loses mass when you take damage, while 
			below 1/2 of your maximum hit points your size category decreases by one, and decreases again when below 
			1/4 of your maximum hit points. Your size increases respectively once you've regained the missing hit 
			points. This effect is negated while shape shifted.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Exhaust.</em></strong> When you're reduced to 0 hit points, you remain 
			semi-conscious and turn into a cloud of smoke, appearing dead to all outward inspection and to spells used 
			to determine status. Additionally you're immune to the restrained condition.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read, and write Common, Ignan and 
			Primordial.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Subrace.</em></strong> An awakened flame chooses their form of flexibility, 
			between large or small.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="true" />
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Igni, Scorch, Burns, Magma, Torch, Heat, Blaze, Inferna, 
			Char, Ember, Flare, Tinder, Pyro, Calcifer</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Igni, Scorch, Burns, Magma, Torch, Heat, Blaze, Inferna, 
			Char, Ember, Flare, Tinder, Pyro, Calcifer</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}}</set>
			<set name="height" modifier="4d10">4'0"</set>
			<set name="weight" modifier="1d4">5 lb.</set>
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<stat name="constitution" value="1" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="25" bonus="base" />
			<stat name="innate speed:fly" value="30" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" />
			<grant type="Language" name="ID_LANGUAGE_IGNAN" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_PRIMORDIAL" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_SCORCH_SKIN" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_SNUFFED_FLAME" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_PURE_FIRE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_MADE_OF_FIRE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_EXHAUST" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AWAKENED_FLAME_SUBRACE" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Scorch Skin" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_SCORCH_SKIN">
		<description>
			<p>When a creature within 5 feet of you deals damage to you or touches your surface flame with any part 
			of their own body. The creature takes 1 fire damage. You can not wear flammable armor, such as leather or 
			hide.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
	<element name="Snuffed Flame" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_SNUFFED_FLAME">
		<description>
			<p>When subjected to an effect or spell that would normally snuff or put out open flames, you are immune 
			to any portion of the spell that would extinguish you, however your speed is reduced by 20-feet until the 
			end of your next turn.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
	<element name="Pure Fire" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_PURE_FIRE">
		<description>
			<p>You have immunity to fire damage. However if you make any significant contact with water you take cold
			damage equal to your level, doubled if more than 1/2 your body is submerged. You know the cantrip control 
			flame, Constitution is your spellcasting ability for this cantrip.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
	<element name="Made of Fire" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_MADE_OF_FIRE">
		<description>
			<p>Your body loses mass when you take damage, while below 1/2 of your maximum hit points your size 
			category decreases by one, and decreases again when below 1/4 of your maximum hit points. Your size 
			increases respectively once you've regained the missing hit points. This effect is negated while shape 
			shifted.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
	<element name="Exhaust" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_EXHAUST">
		<description>
			<p>When you're reduced to 0 hit points, you remain semi-conscious and turn into a cloud of smoke, 
			appearing dead to all outward inspection and to spells used to determine status. Additionally you're 
			immune to the restrained condition.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
	<element name="Awakened Flame Subrace" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AWAKENED_FLAME_SUBRACE">
		<description>
			<p>An awakened flame chooses their form of flexibility, between large or small.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Sub Race" name="Awakened Flame Subrace" supports="Awakened Flame" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Small Flame" type="Sub Race" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_SUB_RACE_SMALL_FLAME">
		<supports>Awakened Flame</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Smaller flexibility awakened flame can shrink down and are harder to hit.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Nimble.</em></strong> Your Dexterity score increases by 2.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Evasive Flame.</em></strong> Your AC is 17, regardless of your DEX 
			modifier or armor.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Reduce.</em></strong> You can decrease your size category by one size 
			as an action and can grow back to your original size as a bonus action.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Gaseous.</em></strong> You gain proficiency in Stealth and can become
			invisible while fully engulfed in any fire source, including torches and lanterns.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Nebulous.</em></strong> You can enter another creature's space and stop 
			there. You can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch wide without squeezing. When doing so you leave
			behind any items you are carrying, and any equipment which you are proficient with merges into your form
			until you exit the space.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="dexterity" value="2" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_EVASIVE_FLAME" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_REDUCE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GASEOUS" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_NEBULOUS" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Evasive Flame" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_EVASIVE_FLAME">
		<description>
			<p>Your AC is 17, regardless of your DEX modifier or armor.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
			<stat name="Nimble" value="7" />
            <stat name="AC" value="NaturalArmor" bonus="Base" />
            <stat name="AC" value="-Dexterity Modifier" />
            <stat name="AC" value="-armor:equipped" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Reduce" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_REDUCE">
		<description>
			<p>You can decrease your size category by one size as an action and can grow back to your original 
			size as a bonus action.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
	<element name="Gaseous" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GASEOUS">
		<description>
			<p>You gain proficiency in Stealth and can become invisible while fully engulfed in any fire source,
			including torches and lanterns.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_STEALTH" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Nebulous" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_NEBULOUS">
		<description>
			<p>You can enter another creature's space and stop there. You can move through a space as narrow as 1
			inch wide without squeezing. When doing so you leave behind any items you are carrying, and any equipment
			which you are proficient with merges into your form until you exit the space.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Large Flame" type="Sub Race" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_SUB_RACE_LARGE_FLAME">
		<supports>Awakened Flame</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Larger flexibility awakened flame can grow larger and are more durable.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Powerful.</em></strong> Your Strength score increases by 2.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Profuse Flame.</em></strong> Your hit point maximum increases by 1, 
			and it increases by 1 every time you gain a level.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Enlarge.</em></strong> You can increase your size category by one size
			as an action and can shrink back to your original size as a bonus action.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Warmth.</em></strong> You can use your large blazing body to warm other
			creatures, cook food, or boil water. And when you or another creatures attempts to, you do so with
			advantage and the effects are twice as beneficial.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Fuel Collection.</em></strong> When any part of your body is in contact
			with a non-magical source of fire, as an action you can recover hit points equal to your proficiency bonus.
			If the source of fire is smaller like a torch, campfire or a lantern, you can only benefit from it once,
			after which the flame is consumed.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="strength" value="2" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_PROFUSE_FLAME" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ENLARGE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_WARMTH" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FUEL_COLLECTION" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Profuse Flame" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_PROFUSE_FLAME">
		<description>
			<p>Your hit point maximum increases by 1, and it increases by 1 every time you gain a level.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
			<stat name="hp" value="level" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Enlarge" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ENLARGE">
		<description>
			<p>You can increase your size category by one size as an action and can shrink back to your original
			size as a bonus action.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
	<element name="Warmth" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_WARMTH">
		<description>
			You can use your large blazing body to warm other creatures, cook food, or boil water. And when you
			or another creatures attempts to, you do so with advantage and the effects are twice as beneficial.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
	<element name="Fuel Collection" type="Racial Trait" source="5e Homebrews from D&D Wiki" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FUEL_COLLECTION">
		<description>
			<p>When any part of your body is in contact with a non-magical source of fire, as an action you can
			recover hit points equal to your proficiency bonus. If the source of fire is smaller like a torch,
			campfire or a lantern, you can only benefit from it once, after which the flame is consumed.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
</elements>